<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications | David Schindler | Academic Website</title>
    <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Publications</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://davidschindler.github.io/media/icon_hu_f58cdc0cf67edc20.png</url>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The value of leadership: Evidence from a large-scale field experiment</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2025-value/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2025-value/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies increasingly make use of team-based organizational structures in complex non-routine tasks. To foster performance in these settings, scholars and practitioners alike have emphasized the potential of leadership. However, its value is difficult to identify in agile and cross-functional teams since leadership is often determined endogenously. To explore the causal impact of leadership, this study randomly encourages teams in a large-scale field experiment (281 teams consisting of 1,273 participants) to select a leader who consistently motivates or consistently coordinates their team. Both encouragements substantially improve team performance and systematically alter team organization, without reducing the originality of solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Efficacy of Tournaments for Nonroutine Team Tasks</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2024-efficacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2024-efficacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tournaments are often used to improve performance in innovation contexts. Tournaments provide monetary incentives but also render teams’ identity and image concerns salient. We study the effects of tournaments on team performance in a nonroutine task and identify the importance of these behavioral aspects. In a field experiment (n&amp;gt;1,700 participants), we vary the salience of team identity, social image concerns, and whether teams face monetary incentives. Increased salience of team identity does not improve performance. Social image motivates the top performers. Additional monetary incentives improve all teams’ outcomes without crowding out teams’ willingness to explore or perform similar tasks again.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The effect of incentives in nonroutine analytical team tasks</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2024-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/englmaier-2024-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the prevalence of nonroutine analytical team tasks in modern economies, little is understood regarding how incentives influence performance in these tasks. In a series of field experiments involving more than 5,000 participants, we investigate how incentives alter behavior in teams working on such a task. We document a positive effect of bonus incentives on performance, even among teams with strong intrinsic motivation. Bonuses also transform team organization by enhancing the demand for leadership. Exogenously increasing teams’ demand for leadership results in performance improvements comparable to those seen with bonus incentives, rendering it as a likely mediator of incentive effects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impulse purchases, gun ownership, and homicides: Evidence from a firearm demand shock</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/koenig-2023-impulse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/koenig-2023-impulse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do firearm purchase delay laws reduce aggregate homicide levels? Using variation from a six-month countrywide gun demand shock in 2012/2013, we show that U.S. states with legislation preventing immediate handgun purchases experienced smaller increases in handgun sales. Our findings indicate that this is likely driven by comparatively lower purchases among impulsive consumers. We then demonstrate that states with purchase delays also witnessed comparatively 2% lower homicide rates during the same period. Further evidence shows that lower handgun sales coincided primarily with fewer impulsive assaults and points toward reduced acts of domestic violence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shocking racial attitudes: black GIs in Europe</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/schindler-2021-shocking/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/schindler-2021-shocking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can attitudes towards minorities, an important cultural trait, be changed? We show that the presence of African American soldiers in the UK during World War II reduced anti-minority prejudice, a result of the positive interactions which took place between soldiers and the local population. The change has been persistent: in locations in which more African American soldiers were posted there are fewer members of and voters for the UK’s leading far-right party, less implicit bias against blacks and fewer individuals professing racial prejudice, all measured around 2010. Our results point towards intergenerational transmission from parents to children as the most likely explanation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unleashing animal spirits: Self-control and overpricing in experimental asset markets</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2019-unleashing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2019-unleashing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One explanation for overpricing on asset markets is a lack of traders’ self-control. We implement the first experiment to address the causal relationship between self-control and systematic overpricing on financial markets. Our setup detects some of the channels through which low individual self-control could transmit into irrational exuberance in markets. Our data indicate a large direct effect of reduced self-control on market overpricing. Low self-control traders report stronger emotions after the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;replication&#34;&gt;Replication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: A recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.5048949&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; has failed to replicate our findings. Please contextualize our results accordingly and if you cite our paper, cite the replication efforts as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk, time pressure, and selection effects</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2019-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2019-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time pressure is a central aspect of economic decision making nowadays. It is therefore natural to ask how time pressure affects decisions, and how to detect individual heterogeneity in the ability to successfully cope with time pressure. In the context of risky decisions, we ask whether a person’s performance under time pressure can be predicted by measurable behavior and traits, and whether such measurement itself may be affected by selection issues. We find that the ability to cope with time pressure varies significantly across decision makers, leading to selected subgroups that differ in terms of their observed behaviors and personal traits. Moreover, measures of cognitive ability and intellectual efficiency jointly predict individuals’ decision quality and ability to keep their decision strategy under time pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overpricing and stake size: On the robustness of results from experimental asset markets</title>
      <link>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2017-overpricing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davidschindler.github.io/publication/kocher-2017-overpricing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assess the effects of a stake size variation on experimental asset markets. Our results show that a fivefold increase in stake size leads to higher trading frequencies. Mispricing and overpricing, however, are not fundamentally different for different stake sizes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
